<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Almansor the learned and victorious king that conquered Spaine. His life and death published by Robert Ashley, out of the librarie of the Uniuersitie of Oxford.</title>
            <title>Verdadera historia del rey Don Rodrigo. Part 2. English. Selections</title>
            <author>Luna, Miguel de, 16th/17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1627</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 108 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16632</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 354</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100094</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99835946</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99835946</idno>
            <idno type="VID">181</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16632)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 181)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 610:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Almansor the learned and victorious king that conquered Spaine. His life and death published by Robert Ashley, out of the librarie of the Uniuersitie of Oxford.</title>
                  <title>Verdadera historia del rey Don Rodrigo. Part 2. English. Selections</title>
                  <author>Luna, Miguel de, 16th/17th cent.</author>
                  <author>Ashley, Robert, 1565-1641.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 79, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by W. Stansby] for Iohn Parker,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1627.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of selections of Part 2 of: Aly Abencusian [i.e. Miguel de Luna].  Verdadera historia del rey Don Rodrigo.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Gathering B in two settings; p. 3, end of line 8: (1) "accor-" or (2) "ac-".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Manṣūr ibn Abī ʻĀmir, 939-1002.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:181:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:181:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>SOR THE LEARNED AND VICTORIOVS King that conquered <hi>Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Life and Death publiſhed By ROBERT ASHLEY <hi>Out of the Librarie of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niuerſitie</hi> of <hi>OXFORD</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Seneca.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Otium tuum non emineat: ſed appareat.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON Printed for <hi>Iohn Parker.</hi> 1627.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:181:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:181:2"/>
            <head>TO OVR GRACIOVS SOVEREIGNE King CHARLES.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His briefe Hiſtorie of the life and death of <hi>Iacob Almanſor: the Victorious,</hi> was intended to the now deceaſſed; yet euer renowmed for Learning, and worthily ſtiled <hi>Iacobus Pacifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> your Royall Father. The death of ſome who had vndertaken the Printing; and the generall Viſitation of this your Realme with ſickneſſe, hath delayed the publiſhing, and altered the deſigne of the Dedication.</p>
            <p>The Wandering Ghoſt of this Learned, Vertuous and Victorious <hi>Almanſor</hi> who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:181:3"/>ſuffered repulſe, being now come into England, and clad with an Engliſh garment preſſeth into your Kingly preſence, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecteth condigne entertainment. Though the Storie bee ancient, and your Time and Religion alſo from his much different<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet he hopeth that Vertue and Valour are neuer out of ſeaſon: Nor the Wiſdome and Induſtrie of any, bee hee Heathen, Mahometan, or Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, to be diſeſteemed.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Alexander</hi> was enflamed with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Achilles,</hi> who liued long before him: <hi>Caeſar</hi> by that of <hi>Alexander</hi> of a different time and Nation; the one being a Grecian King of Macedon: the other but a priuate Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of Rome: and <hi>Scipio</hi> a young Roman that triumphed ouer Africke, was animated by the Hiſtorie of <hi>Cyrus</hi> the great King of Perſia deſcribed by <hi>Xenophon.</hi> So if at this day among Chriſtians, they that haue any heart, are enkindled in their courage, when they reade of the Clemencie of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> the Magnanimitie of <hi>Alexander,</hi> the Integritie of <hi>Aristides,</hi> the Conſtancie of <hi>Cato,</hi> or the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e and Goodneſſe of <hi>Traian,</hi> being but Heathens of former Ages, that knew not
<pb facs="tcp:181:3"/>Chriſt, nor Chriſtian Pietie: with more reaſon <hi>Almanſor</hi> of much later Age, though a misbeleeuing Mahometan may well ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, euen in theſe times, among the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of perfect Pietie, his Vertues ſhould not be vnregarded; nor his well ordered life and death be buried in obliuion.</p>
            <p>I leaue them that liſt to diſpute the truth of his Hiſtorie; or whether it bee not a pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of Perfection deuiſed: as many haue ſuppoſed the like of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> deſcribed by <hi>Xeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon.</hi> Howſoeuer the Truth bee; I hold the one and the other of better vſe, being thus publiſhed, then to be buried in ſilence.</p>
            <p>I doubt not but your Royall Fathers In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and your owne worthy diſpoſition hath figured in your noble breſt many wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thier Chriſtian patternes for Imitation: Yet by comparing our ſelues with Heathens, with Infidels, with Mahometans, and other Misbeleeuers; we attaine the better and clee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer knowledge of our aduantages and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects. Hereof your aduenturous Trauailes in your younger yeares haue giuen you good experience<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Hee that knoweth no Countrey but his own, knoweth not the worth or wants
<pb facs="tcp:181:4"/>of his owne: <hi>Commendandus ante omnes qui ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientiam toto orbe requirit</hi> ſaith <hi>Marſilius:</hi> which oportunitie of perſonall Trauaile being not alwayes permitted; it muſt bee ſupplyed by Bookes and Hiſtories. The aduertiſement following will informe the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars how this briefe Hiſtorie came to the Preſenters hands, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>In all humilitie, your Maieſties deuoted Subiect,</hi> Robert Aſhley.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:181:4"/>
            <head>An Aduertiſement.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing during my younger yeares had ſome trayning in the Arts, and Learned Languages in the famous Vniuerſitie of Oxford: and by aduice of experienced friends hauing after ſeriouſly ſought to attaine the knowledge of the Lawes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which wee liue, in the place where they are profeſſed: and hauing beene long ſince ingaged and denominated among the Profeſſors thereof: yet finding the practiſe to haue ebbes and tydes; (as haue for the moſt part all other humane employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments) I haue ſtolne and ſnatched at vacant times ſome oportunities; what by Trauaile, Bookes, and Conference; to get ſome knowledge of forreigne Countries, and vulgar Languages: especially thoſe of our Neighbours (I meane the French and Dutch, the Spaniſh and Italian) that by the peruſing of their Writings, I might alſo bee made partaker of the Wiſdome of thoſe Nations: hauing beene long of this opinion. That as no one
<pb facs="tcp:181:5"/>ſoyle or territorie, yeeldeth all fruits alike, ſo no one Climate or Region affordeth all kind of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in full meaſure.</p>
            <p>With this reſolution, being not letted by other occaſions, J ſpent the beſt houres of ſome few Weekes, not many yeeres ſithence in a ſuperficiall ſuruey of the famous <hi>Librarie</hi> of that flouriſhing <hi>Vniuerſitie,</hi> where I had beene trayned: which I found richly repleniſhed with Bookes of all Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Faculties: not only in the Learned Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, <hi>Latine, Greeke,</hi> and <hi>Hebrew:</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the vulgar Tongues of our Neighbour Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions) but euen with ſome furniture as well of <hi>Manuſcripts</hi> as of printed Copies in the <hi>Arabian, Aethiopian,</hi> and <hi>Armenian</hi> Languages; with the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Wiſdome and Characters (not ſpeaking of the <hi>Chaldaick,</hi> and <hi>Syriak;</hi> becauſe they are accounted by many but as Hebrew-dialects). There are alſo ſome <hi>Turkiſh</hi> &amp; <hi>Perſian Manuſcripts; Indian, Malayan,</hi> and <hi>Mexican Characters and Writings.</hi> Yea, <hi>China</hi> it ſelfe (being thought by many to bee inacceſsible to Strangers) though by ſundry Seas and Lands it bee farre ſeparated from vs, hath vouchſafed to inrich this great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazin, or Storehouſe of Learning, with diuers and ſundry parcels of her Wiſdome imprinted in her ſtrange Characters.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:181:5"/>
            <p>Amongſt the reſt I happened on an <hi>Arabian Hiſtorie</hi> concerning the loſſe of <hi>Spaine</hi> by <hi>Rode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigo King of the Gothes,</hi> which by command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>King</hi> Philip the Second, was tranſlated into <hi>Spaniſh</hi> out of the <hi>Arabian Copie</hi> remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the <hi>Eſcurial:</hi> where I my ſelfe haue ſeene a <hi>glorious golden Librarie of Arabian Bookes.</hi> In the midſt of that Hiſtorie, I found a Summarie Collection, or obſernation of the life and death of <hi>a Learned Arabian King Iacob Almanſor</hi> the Conquerour of <hi>Spaine.</hi> Of the excellencie of this great King, ſome hauing heard and read that among other his vertues, hee was an infinite louer of Learning, hauing <hi>aſſembled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in his Librarie fiftie fiue thouſand Bookes in an ignorant Age: when long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Inuention of Printing, all Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Learning, were only preſerued by the laborious induſtrie of the Writers hand and Pen.</hi> Weighing alſo his wiſe diſtribution of his time with his exact Iuſtice, Wiſdome of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, his Temperance of Dyet, Fortitude, and Prudence in his Militarie affaires; with the Prosperitie of his Conqueſts; and ſucceſſe of all his enterprizes: they became deſirous to bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted,
<pb facs="tcp:181:6"/>with the particulars of his life; and longed to haue it communicated vnto them, in a Tongue which they better vnderſtood. To their honeſt deſire, hauing oportunitie in my hand, I thought it conuenient to giue ſatisfaction by tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating it out of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Copie which was prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at <hi>Saragoza 1603.</hi> remayning in that vnpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralleld rare <hi>Librarie</hi> of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niuerſitie of <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> and therehence out of <hi>the larger Hiſtorie of the Conqueſt of Spaine by the Moores,</hi> (being then the Subiects of this <hi>Almanſor</hi>) by me excerpted and publiſhed. I preſent it to publicke view, that Chriſtians finding their vertuous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrie to be equalled or ouermatched by <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometans</hi> may the rather be excited to a diſdainfull emulation of their worthieſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuours.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:181:6"/>
            <head>The Letter written by King <hi>Aben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cirix</hi> to the <hi>Alcayde Ali Abenzufian</hi> Viceroy and Gouernour of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces of <hi>Deuque</hi> in <hi>Arabia,</hi> by which he commandeth him to write the life of King <hi>Iacob Almanſor.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>PRayſe bee giuen to God alone, <hi>Amen.</hi> The high and highly honoured King Gouernour of the Moores, of noble diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, defender of Mahometiſme, who ſhiel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth himſelfe vnder the protection of the moſt high God, <hi>Ali Abencirix:</hi> To the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, Noble, Wiſe, Diſcreet, Learned, and Generous Gentleman the <hi>Alcayde Ali Aben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zufian</hi> our Vice-roy and Gouernour of the Prouinces of <hi>Deuque:</hi> wee ſend greeting. And after our ſalutation, wee ſay that conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the great wiſedome with which the King <hi>Abilgualit Miramamolin Iacob Almanſor,</hi> our great Grandfather and Lord gouerned his Kingdomes in peace; and the fortitude with which hee preſerued his Subiects, and rooted out their Enemies; and the Iuſtice with which he conſerued his Eſtates; and the
<pb facs="tcp:181:7"/>Temperance, vſed by him in all his actions and deeds, which of all the World are admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; and all the Bookes repleniſhed with his Sayings and Sentences in all Sciences; and his notable Deeds of Armes, with his great ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and good cuſtomes to bee ſuch as all the Princes of the World may take an example and patterne thereby to rule and gouerne their Common-weales, and to liue in tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quilitie. We haue thought meete and conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient that the Diſcourſe of his Life ſhould be gathered together, and orderly compiled and written in one Booke, (and not be left as it is now ſcattered in many parts:) as well for our owne conſolation, as for the Imitation of this great King in his cuſtomes and manner of liuing: to make our profit and vſe of them in matters that concerne our Gouernment and our Common-weales; and to this effect hauing that regard which wee haue of your perſon, abilitie, and learning, together with your trayning and continuall attendance and ſeruice in his Royall Palace from your child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, being alwayes inward with him, in ſuch ſort that no other how learned ſoeuer can better ſet forth and write his life and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
<pb facs="tcp:181:7"/>then you. Wee charge and command you that with conuenient breuitie auoyding prolixitie, and writing the Truth with that obligation which is due to the fidelitie of an Hiſtorie: (whereof by reaſon of your good zeale and punctuall manner of writing ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued by you, we reſt aſſured) you write a Booke of his life and cuſtomes, together with the manner and order how this good King ruled and gouerned his Kingdomes till his life ended by death: which you ſhall entitle the bright Mirrour of Princes; whereby you ſhall doe vs acceptable ſeruice. In this Booke you ſhall alſo doe well to ſet downe what eſpeciall things a good King is to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, to make himſelfe beloued of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, and feared of his enemies. All which may ſerue vs in ſteed of a Guide or a Light with the fauour and helpe of our Souereigne God for the ruling and gouerning of our Kingdomes and Common-weales, that they may enioy Peace and tranquillitie; and our ſelues quietneſſe of minde and clearneſſe of Conſcience. Whereof through that confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence we haue in your worthineſſe we make no doubt. God haue you in his keeping.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:181:8"/>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From our Royall Palace of <hi>Zarbal;</hi> 
                  <date>the fourth day of the Moone of <hi>Mobarram,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The date is anſwerable to the yeare <hi>An. Chriſti</hi> 731.</note> 
                     <hi>the hundred and tenth yeare of the Hixera.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="reply">
            <head>The Letter of the <hi>Alcayde Ali Aben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zuſian</hi> in anſwer of the former by which hee dedicateth the Worke to King <hi>Ali Abencirix.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>PRayſe be giuen to our Souereigne God. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi> To the much renowmed and that with reaſon for hu great skill in Gouerning, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in conſeruing, and Fortitude in mayntayning his Subiects in Peace, the valiant Warrior, ſtrong and couragious defender of <hi>Moriſme,</hi> of high and famous Progeny and Race, the great <hi>Calipha,</hi> the rooter out of his Enemies, the King highly honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and of complete power, <hi>Ali Abeneirix;</hi> the highest God continue his good deſires. And in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to his Letter dated in the Palace of <hi>Zarbal,</hi> the fourth day of the Moone of <hi>Moharram</hi> this preſent yeare; by which I was commanded to write a Booke of the cuſtomes, conditions and manner of life of his Predeceſſor King <hi>Abilgua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit
<pb facs="tcp:181:8"/>Iacob Almanſor,</hi> and therewith alſo to ſet downe and declare what other Rules a good Prince ought to obſerue: for the fulfilling whereof I haue ſtolne from other my great buſineſſe, ſome parts of the night bereauing my ſelfe of that ſleepe which for my weake and wearied bodie had beane requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite; and in theſe twelue briefe and compendious Chapters which accompany this my Letter I haue rehearſed and regiſtred the life and cuſtomes, and the manner of Ruling and Gouerning with this great King and Gouernour vſed in the time of his prosperous Raigne: and I am alſo of this opinion that without any farther addition of thoſe Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings which are written by the Phyloſophers and other graue and learned Authors, one may gather out of this as much fruit as he deſireth. I am an eye witneſſe of all that I write, hauing ſerued him in his Chamber and other Offices in his Royall Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, of no ſmall importance, more then twentie yeares (as is well knowne to thoſe that frequented the Court in his time) and haue ſeene and knowne his cuſtomes and conditions, vprightneſſe and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie, Gouernment and manner of adminiſtring juſtice both in Peace and Warre. Now in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of writing I worke two effects, the accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of a Royall commandement; and the regiſtring
<pb facs="tcp:181:9"/>of the vertuous and laudable morall cuſtomes of ſo good a King. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ouchſafe to accept my good will and pardon my faults and ouerſights if there bee any in this Treatiſe (whereof I doubt not there may bee many) attributing them rather to my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfulneſſe, then to any wilfull imperfection, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſſe or negligence, eyther againſt the fidelitie of an Hiſtorie, or the loyaltie which is due to his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Seruice; whom our Souereigne God, continue in his Protection.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From the Citie of <hi>Deuque</hi> 
                  <date>the fifteenth day of the Moone of <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beh</hi> the firſt,<note place="margin">This date a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth with the month of Anguſt of the yeare of Chriſt, 731.</note> the one hundred and tenth yeere of the <hi>Hixera.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:181:9"/>
            <head>THE LIFE AND Death of IACOB ALMANSOR, <hi>an Arabian Mahometan King,</hi> written in the Arabicke TONGVE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the Deſcendence and Genealogie of the King <hi>Abilgualit Miramamolin Iacob Alman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor,</hi> and of ſome of his memorable deeds.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Bilgualit Miramamolin Iacob Almanſor</hi> was the ſonne of the great Caliph, the ſuſtayner of <hi>Moriſme Abihabdi Allahi Abilgualit Abin<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Abni Malique;</hi> and nephew of the great Caliph <hi>Abni Abel Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen. Motaleb</hi> of famous and high Linage,<note place="margin">Solar:</note> the renowmed race and houſe of the Gentile
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:181:10"/>Kings of <hi>Arabia.</hi> Hee was borne in the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth yeare of the <hi>Higera,</hi> on the ſecond day of the Moone of <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>buel;</hi> hauing attained with ſound and perfect health to fifteene yeares of Age, he began to ſhow ſo great courage and Inclination to Armes and Learning, that hee cauſed admiration in his Maſters, who had the charge and gouernment of him. For he was at this age ſo skilfull in the ſeuen Libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Sciences, that they who were the moſt learned in them, ſpake of them in his preſence With much feare and baſhfulneſſe, for at euery other word he corrected the Imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions which proceeded out of their Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. And at the eighteenth yeare of his age he wrote the three bookes of Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes and Aſtrologie, which are ſo renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at this day amongſt the <hi>Arabians.</hi> Hee wrote alſo the abridgement of Hiſtories, the great Art of <hi>Algebra;</hi> and the booke of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of the militarie Art, and that which hee entitled <hi>The Mirrour of Princes.</hi> At the one and twentieth yeare of his age he wrote the three Bookes of Philoſophie vpon the Texts of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> in forme of a Comment. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, that which was moſt to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:181:10"/>was, that at the fiue and twentieth yeare of his age, he ſpake eleuen Languages, reading and writing them as perfectly as the very Naturals themſelues. The King <hi>Abil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gualit</hi> his father being himſelfe a wiſe man, yet vndertooke no enterpriſe without his counſell and aduice, becauſe hee found that in ſo doing his affaires euer ſucceeded accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his hearts deſire. This valorous Prince hauing liued after this manner a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſeaſon, and hauing ordayned a <hi>Iurgo di canas,</hi> and other diſports, called vnto them the great <hi>Alcaydes,</hi> who were Gouernors of his Kingdomes, one of which at his comming preſented to the King <hi>Abilgualit</hi> his father an <hi>Alfange,</hi> which is a Sword or Cimiter of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable value: for the handle was of the fineſt Emerald: the pommell of a ſtone cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a Balais:<note place="margin">Tabeli.</note> the ſcabberd and chape hilt of fine gold wrought with the hammer: with ſundry ſorts of precious ſtones enchaced;<note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ia.</note> and the blade moſt excellently damasked. Some of the <hi>Alcaydes</hi> hauing ſeene and handled it from hand to hand, they all concluded in ſaying, that were it but halfe a hands bredth longer, it would then be the beſt weapon in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:181:11"/>the world: whereat the King <hi>Abilgualit</hi> was much diſtaſted becauſe hee had taken a great liking thereof; and therfore cauſed the Prince <hi>Jacob Almanſor</hi> to be called that hee might ſee it, and giue his iudgement thereon: admoniſhing the <hi>Alcaydes,</hi> that none ſhould aduertiſe him of the fault they found; who being come to his preſence, he commanded that the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fange ſhould be ſhowne him, who was ſo wel pleaſed with the ſight of it, that he preſently ſpake theſe words: This Weapon is worth a Citie. The King his father replyed, that hee ſhould looke well theron, and conſider what fault there was to be found therein: but hee ſaid hee found none, the thing being as well framed and wrought as he could deſire. Then his father the King <hi>Abilgualit</hi> acquainted him how the <hi>Alcaydes</hi> did ſay, that the Blade was too ſhort. Whereat the Prince taking the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fange in his hand, ſaid with a ſmiling counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance theſe words. To the hardie and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious caualiers, no weapon no weapon is too ſhort, and then ſtepping with his right foot one ſtep forwards with the Alfange in his hand, proſecuting his reaſon, hee ſaid; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe with one pace forward it will bee made
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:181:11"/>as long as one would deſire. This his ſpeech was ſo pleaſing to his father <hi>Abilgualit</hi> that he preſently caſt his armes about his neck and embraced him, ſaying; Certainly my Sonne thou mayeſt well ſeeke out other Kingdoms to conquer, for thoſe which I ſhall leaue thee are too few, for that wiſdome and valour which the Soueraigne God hath giuen thee: and girding the Alfange about him, hee ſaid, that it could not belong to any but to him, ſince hee found no fault with it. This being thus ended, the Prince went downe with all the <hi>Alcaydes</hi> that were preſent, to play at the Canes, and at other deuices in ſuch ſort that all admired his dexterity in deuiſing &amp; gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſuch delightfull diſports. The next day with many gracious fauours he diſpatched thoſe <hi>Alcaydes.</hi> Which done, hee ſaid it were not reaſonable to ſhew himſelfe gracious on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the <hi>Alcaydes</hi> of his Kingdomes, and to leaue his poore Subiects comfortleſſe and vnrewarded. With which reſolution, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded all the poore about his Court to bee called, that they might alſo bee partakers of his bounty; and when they were come, hee placed himſelfe at the Gate of his Treaſurie,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:181:12"/>and as they paſſed by him, hee gaue to euery one of them a handfull of gold coyne vntold which hauing done, he vnderſtood after by his tellers, that hee had that day diſtributed two and twentie Arrobas;<note place="margin">Arrobas.</note> and thirteene pounds of gold. This being reported to his father <hi>Abilgualit,</hi> hee was reprehended by him, as being too free, and aduiſed him to ſtay his hand, leſt otherwiſe he might becom poore, ſaying, that a King without his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is like a dead man among the liuing. But the Prince anſwered, that he might rather be ſaid to be dead, that is cloſe fiſted towards his followers, becauſe hee could not expect any comfort of them in his neceſſitie, and in the day of his diſtreſſe: and that hee was not borne but to doe good, in imitation of his Creator, who vſed ſo much clemencie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his creatures; whoſe ſecond cauſe or Inſtrument hee eſteemed himſelfe here on earth; and that none might iuſtly reprehend him in that behalfe, ſeeing hee conſidered that nothing was more certaine then death, and that he could carrie nothing out of this life but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> poore ſhrowd or <hi>Winding ſheet,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mortaia.</note> and thoſe good or euill deeds which he had done
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:181:12"/>in this life, to giue accompt of them to that high moſt omnipotent God, as to a iuſt Iudge at the day of that fearefull finall Iudgement. Theſe reaſons were ſo agrecable to his father <hi>Abilgualit,</hi> that conſidering well the great worth of the Prince, he or dayned eft-ſoones in his life and Kingdomes ſuch order and courſe as the next Chapter declares.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How the King <hi>Abilgualit</hi> reſigned his Kingdom to his Sonne <hi>Iacob Almanſor,</hi> and retired to a ſolitarie life.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He King <hi>Abilgualit</hi> perceiuing the great valour of his Sonne the Prince, <hi>Iacob Almanſor,</hi> and that he himſelfe was old, being aboue ſeuentie yeares of Age, he reſolued to reſigne his Kingdome into his hands, and to retire to his reſt: and reſigned the ſame according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, with the agreement and conſent of the great <hi>Alcaydes</hi> of his Kingdome, in ſuch ſort, that the Prince <hi>Iacob Almanſor</hi> was crowned and ſworne for King the tenth day of the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:181:13"/>Moone of <hi>Moharram,</hi> three and thirtie yeeres of the <hi>Higera</hi> being then fully complete,<note place="margin">Aune Chr. <hi>654.</hi> Ian.</note> which Coronation was confirmed the third day of the Moone of <hi>Rabeh,</hi> being the ſecond of that yeare.</p>
               <p>Hauing began his Raigne and Gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he tooke alſo a new habit in his condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, kind, and manner of Liuing, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are worth the remembring, I will not forbeare to rehearſe at large in this briefe Treatiſe. For, contrary to that gallantry and brauerie which he vſed whiles he was Prince hee clothed himſelfe in the plaineſt ſort that hee could deuiſe. Hee put on ſuch a modeſt ſettled countenance, that none of thoſe that ſerued him could know by his outward car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage whether he were ſorrowfull or ioyfull. In good and ill ſucceſſe his viſage was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies alike; and hee carried himſelfe in ſuch ſort to wards thoſe of his houſe, that the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance was euen between Loue and Feare; for neither for great ſeruice done, nor for neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect or omiſſion of dutie, could they know whether they were in fauour or diſgrace.</p>
               <p>Hee diuided the dayes of the weeke after this manner. The Friday for matters of his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:181:13"/>Religion, in which hee was very deuout. The Saturday for matters of Iuſtice. The Sunday for matters of Warre. The Munday for the gouernment of his Kingdomes. The Tueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day and Wedneſday for his Recreation: and his priuate affaires, and the Thurſday for matters of Learning.</p>
               <p>The Friday as wee haue ſaid, hee medled with no affaires or buſineſſe, but went in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnitie to the great Meſquita,<note place="margin">Eala.</note> being his Church, in this manner. Hee ſet forth from his Palace attended with fiue hundred foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, with their Alfanges; two of which on each ſide of their Captaine, carried their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Alſanges vpright, the points vpward; &amp; their Captaine hauing his Alfange girt about him, as all the reſt, therby ſignifying the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude and iuſtice by which hee maintayned his Kingdomes in peace. Next before thoſe of his Guard went two hundred horſemen very well appointed, with their Captaine and Standard Royall, armed with their Curiaſſes, Alfanges, Lances and Targets. Neere vnto his Perſon went the <hi>Alguazil Mayor</hi> or Camp-maſter, after whom the Councell of Warre, then his Councell of State or Gouernement
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:181:14"/>of his Kingdomes, and the <hi>Cadi</hi> or his chiefe Iuſtice. In each of theſe Counſailes hee had foure Counſellors, the ancient of which was Preſident. The <hi>Alcayde</hi> that was Captayne Generall or Admirall of the Sea, if hee were in Court was before all, next about his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. The <hi>Alfaqui Mayor</hi> of the Meſquita be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the great Prelate or Church-man, went on his left hand; his eldeſt Sonne on his right, and the reſt of his Sonnes before him. Being come to the Meſquita, they went in all to their prayers; which being ended, they retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the ſame order to the Palace; where was placed a Seate for the King neere vnto a Fountaine, where being ſate, hee receiued the Petitions and Supplications of all ſutors, whether Courtiers or ſtrangers. Then hee aroſe, and an Huiſſier of his Chamber with a lowde voyce that all might heare, ſaid in this manner. <hi>All they that haue giuen any Memori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls or Bills this day to the King</hi> Miramamolin Almanſor <hi>our Lord (whom the Soueraigne God make victorious) are to repaire to morrow to his Royall Audience, where hee will render them Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</hi> Then hee aroſe and went to his repaſt, and a Mayordomo being as a Maſter of his
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:181:14"/>houſhold, ſaid after this manner alowd that all might heare. <hi>All Sutors rich and poore that ſue vnto the King, are to ſtay and receiue their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in the Royall Palace, as hath beene accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed.</hi> Preſently were prepared three Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of ſuch length and capacitie that two hundred perſons might ſit at euery of them. The firſt for the <hi>Alcaydes</hi> and principall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. The ſecond for thoſe of the middle ſort. The third was for the poorer, and for the ſeruants of the <hi>Alcaydes,</hi> which Tables were all furniſhed with ſuch aboundance of Prouiſion, as became the houſe of ſo mighty a King. And if there were much people, they tooke each of them his turne, and were all filled and ſatisfied. Hee tooke his repaſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies in priuate, &amp; neuer in publike, though he were in campe. Neither in time of Peace or of Warre did hee vſe to eate or drinke in veſſell of gold or ſiluer, albeit he had many, neither had hee any Phyſician to direct his Diet, much leſſe any <hi>Alcayde</hi> to take the eſſay, neither more then two ſeruants to ſerue him at the Table: neither did he eate more then of two kinds of meate. For hee ſaid, that if any meant to poyſon him, the taking of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:181:15"/>eſſayes would not preuent his death; and that two were ſufficient to ſerue anyone man; that in time of Health he had no need of the Phyſician; and that the man that could not tell how to preſerue himſelfe from being ſick by ſurfet of meat or ſuperfluitie of drinke, was rather to bee ranked among beaſts then reaſonable men. After meat his exerciſe was alwaies moderate; and about foure houres after he went to the Bath, wherein he ſtayed an houre, and then walked vntill it was time to retire to his reſt. Then came his Magor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domo and gaue him a briefe account of that which was vnder his charge, and what hee had done that day, aduertiſing if there were any notable thing deſeruing chaſtiſement or reward in any of his houſhold, that hee might therein take ſuch order as was moſt conuenient, which he did accordingly with great wiſdome and celeritie. Then he betooke himſelfe to his reſt. It was a thing worthy to bee obſerued, that during all his life hee euer went to bed before the third part of the night were ſpent, and alwaies aroſe before the Sunne peeped out of the Eaſt: except it were in that laſt ſickneſſe, whereof hee died. Hee
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:181:15"/>ſlept not by day, neither in Winter nor Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; nor ate any more then once. Hee had a Prouerbe written on his Royall Seat, where he vſually ſate to doe Iuſtice, which was writ ten in Letters of Gold in the leſſer Arabicke verſe, which ſaid after this manner.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Sixe Excellencies are found in a man <hi>worthy to bee noted.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>THe firſt is Iuſtice which chiefely appertaineth to Kings.</l>
                     <l>The ſecond is Charitie, belonging eſpecially to the rich.</l>
                     <l>The third is Patience, whereof the poore haue moſt vſe.</l>
                     <l>The fourth is Chaſtitie, whereof young men haue moſt neede.</l>
                     <l>The fift is Contempt of the World, which is principally ſeene in the wiſe.</l>
                     <l>The ſixt is ſhamefaſtneſſe, which is moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended in women.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:181:16"/>
               <p>Somewhat lower the verſe ſaid <hi>after this manner.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <p>THe King that obſerueth not Iuſtice is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to the Cloud that yeeldeth no raine.</p>
                  <p>The rich man hauing no charity is like the Tree that beareth no fruit.</p>
                  <p>The poore which is without Patience reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth the Riuer which is without Water:</p>
                  <p>The yong man that hath no chaſtitie is as a Torch that lendeth no light.</p>
                  <p>The wiſe man that deſpiſeth not the world is compared to the barren and fruitleſſe ground.</p>
                  <p>The woman that hath no ſhame faſtneſſe is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled to meat without Salt.</p>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Another Prouerbe hee had written ouer his Bed in like verſe, which ſayeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <p>The man which conſumeth the day in eating and drinking, and in other delights and pleaſures, and all the whole night in ſleeping: by doing onely that which belongeth to beaſts, becommeth like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. Praiſed be God for euer and euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:181:16"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the manner obſerued by the King <hi>Iacob Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manfor,</hi> in adminiſtring Iustice.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His King <hi>Abilgualit Iacob Alman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor</hi> was ſuch a Louer of Truth, that it was not obſerued in him, either whiles hee was a Child, a Prince, or a crowned King, that euer he told any lye or ſpake any vntruth. Hee loued alwaies to ſpeake the Truth himſelfe, expecting the like in them that negotiated with him; for he ſaid, that a greater miſery could not befal a man in this life then to be a lyer, who with more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon might be called the Diuels diſciple, then accounted a reaſonable man: becauſe there are found in a lyer all the miſchiefes in the world, being euer vniuſt, a falſe witneſſe bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, a very traitor to the Truth, and ſuch as was not fit to treat with any man, or to looke him in the face. With this zeale did he cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten ſo rigoruſly whomſoeuer he found with a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e, that it coſt many little leſſe then their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, for according to the qualitie of the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence; ſome hee cauſed cruelly to be whipt, others to haue the tip of their tongue cut off,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:181:17"/>condemning them for infamous; and that their Teſtimonie might not bee receiued, in any ſuite or controuerſie. And if it were to the preiudice of a third perſon he condemned them to death. For hee ſaid that all quarrels and debates, wounding and killing, with all other their appurtenances, were occaſioned onely of this, that men ſpake not the Truth one to another. All his Subiects knowing in what deteſtation he held falſehood, durſt not make any vniuſt demand before him, or any of his <hi>Alcaydes,</hi> who had the Gouernment; which foundation being laide, each Saturday hee ſate in his Seate, in the Royall Audience, and his Cadi or chiefe Iuſtice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greee lower at his feet, with thoſe Memorials, Petitions, and Bils which he had receiued on the Friday; Hauing peruſed and placed them in order as he receiued them, hee called the parties, and they propoſing the Iuſtice of their cauſes, in ſuch ſort, that euery one was heard for himſelfe, in his ſeuerall pretentions and allegations. The Cadi gaue Iudgement, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to euery one his right: and becauſe they durſt not lye by reaſon of the cruell chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in that behalfe, beſides that there were
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:181:17"/>the fewer cauſes and complaints, they were alſo diſpatched with much ſpeed, and very ſummarily, in regard that there needed no proofes but onely the Confeſſion of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, vnleſſe they were matters concerning the value of goods or of a higher nature, in which caſes he referred them to his Councel, for auerring the Truth; and when ſuch kinde of pleas were in his Court, they receiued an end at the ſecond Audience, which was the next weeke: and if they were out of the Court in ſome other Citie they were to be determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned within a fortnight or fifteene dayes after they began, reſeruing the definitiue ſentence to himſelfe, if the parties did not conforme themſelues, or the Iudges were doubtfull therein. In criminall cauſes he neuer detay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned any priſoner aboue three dayes; and for hainous crimes aboue nine; and if any that was poore were in priſon for debt, hee paid it out of his owne treaſure, ſo that by oath or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> were auerred that hee had no g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s to make payment. And being ſo ſtrict an obſeruer of Truth, there were very few Suits in Law, and thoſe alſo very neceſſarie and compulſorie, for he was ſo feared of his
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:181:18"/>Subiects, that rather then to appeare before him for matter of Iuſtice, they agreed among themſelues without ſute or debate, by which meanes they were ſo careful to deale vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one with another, that they liued in great peace. He chaſtiſed <hi>theoues</hi> ſo ſeuerely, that none durſt take any thing from other, neither in Citie nor Countrie, as well in deſert as in peopled places. And in ſo great awe they were of him, that if any one had loſt ought in the ſtreete or market place, none durſt med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle therewith, otherwiſe then to leaue it at the next ſhop, and cauſe it to be cryed til the ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner were found to whom it was to bee reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. This King was ſo feared in all his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes,<note place="margin">This cuſtome was vſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Moores of Granada euen to our dayes; and ſeemeth in a manner naturall to them.</note> and his Subiects liued in ſuch ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that one accident which befell in his time I hold worthy to bee here related. Which is, that after hee had conquered and wonne the Kingdome of Spaine from the King <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drigo</hi> a Chriſtian by Profeſſion, and had peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled and bordered it as he thought conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, he ſent an <hi>Alcayde</hi> a great fauorite of his, called <hi>Abraham Maanya</hi> to viſit the ſame, who being arriued there, and going about in viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, paſſed through a great playne which
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:181:18"/>lyeth betweene two Cities, where meeting with a woman that was alone vnaccompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, yet not vnhandſome, nor euill fauoured, he maruailed much, asking her how ſhee durſt aduenture to goe alone through that vnpeopled place, reprouing and reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding her boldneſſe: who anſwered him in this manner; While our good King <hi>Iacob Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſor</hi> liueth (whom I pray the Soueraigne God to grant a long life and victorie ouer his enemies.) Wee may all trauaile ſecurely through his Kingdomes, and as ſafely in the wild fields, as in Townes and Cities. The <hi>Alcayde</hi> maruailing much at her words; when he was returned into the preſence of his Lord <hi>Miramamolin Almanſor,</hi> to giue him account of ſuch things as hee had recommended to his care in his Viſitation of Spaine, amongſt other memorable things, related vnto him, how he met with the woman on that vninha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited plaine, and how hee reprehending her boldneſſe in aduenturing alone in a place where ſome outrage might eaſily bee done her, ſhee had anſwered him in that confident manner before rehearſed; and <hi>Miramamolin Almanſor</hi> enquiring what he had replyed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:181:19"/>her, he ſaid that hee had told her that ſhee was a foole to imagine any ſuch ſecuritie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if any were diſpoſed to doe her any wrong or dammage, <hi>Miramamolin Almanſor</hi> could yeeld her little helpe or ſuccour being then in Arabia, ſo farre remote from Spaine. The King <hi>Almanſor</hi> was ſo much offended with thoſe words, that hee forthwith com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to prepare himſelfe to returne eft-ſoones for Spaine, for he had great vſe of his Seruice there for adminiſtration of his Royall Iuſtice, and with great diſſimulation he wrote preſently a letter to the Gouernour of Spaine, called <hi>Abulcacim Abdiluar,</hi> enclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing therein the <hi>Alcaydes</hi> owne Confeſſion, commanding, that as ſoone as hee came hee ſhould empale him in that very place where he met with the woman, proclaiming his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence in this manner. That King <hi>Almanſor</hi> commanded this Iuſtice to bee executed on that <hi>Alcayde,</hi> for his bold attempt of ſpeaking with the woman in that deſert place, &amp; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for putting her in doubt of the ſecuritie of her perſon, and ſaying that the King <hi>Iacob Almanſor</hi> could not helpe or ſuccor her, liuing in Arabia ſo farre remote from Spaine. This
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:181:19"/>
                  <hi>Alcayde</hi> forth with departed, not knowing that he carried his death incloſed in that let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and as ſoone as hee came to the <hi>Alcayde Abdiluar,</hi> then Gouernor of Spaine, hauing read it, he cauſed him to be taken; and execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te on him that ſentence of the King <hi>Mirama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molin</hi> his Lord. This caſe was much noted of all the <hi>Alcaydes,</hi> Gouernours, and Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of thoſe Kingdomes, as well Moores as Chriſtians. And this deed may ſerue for an example of many like, which he commanded to be done in his Kingdomes worthy of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, which, to auoide prolixitie, I forbeare to rehearſe in this briefe treatiſe,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the manner and order which hee held in his Councell of Warre and militarie Affaires, and how he made his Conqueſts by Sea and by Land.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>N the Sunday (as wee haue men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned alreadie) the King <hi>Iacob Almanſor</hi> medled with no other affaires but militarie; for which he had foure <hi>Alcaydes,</hi> named and choſen his
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:181:20"/>Counſellors for the warres, of which the moſt ancient was the <hi>Preſident,</hi> to whom it belonged to receiue all the Letters and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſements which were ſent by the <hi>Alcaydes</hi> that were Gouernours of the Kingdomes, where the garriſons &amp; Sooldiers reſided, and he peruſed them and prepared them againſt this day. Then the King <hi>Almanſor</hi> entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Counſaile with them, and for anſwer to them being but ordinarie affaires, it was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorſed on the letters, by which the antient <hi>Alcayde</hi> had his direction what anſwer hee ſhould returne them. But when he intended any warres or pretended any conqueſt, hee called no Counſell, but wherein the <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> of his forces by Land, and the <hi>Alcayde</hi> who as <hi>chiefe Admirall was Generall by Sea,</hi> were alſo preſent. For he ſaid, it was not rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſonable to preferre the vote or voyce of any his Counſellors, or his owne, before that of theſe great Captaines, who were to execute whatſoeuer hee and his Counſell ſhould or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine; therefore being called, they entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Councell: and the King <hi>Iacob Almanſor</hi> propoſing and ſignifying vnto them what he intended; the yongeſt <hi>Alcayde</hi> of the Counſel
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:181:20"/>had the <hi>charge to oppoſe</hi> what Incoueniences hee found in that which the King had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded; and the reſt conferred preſently concerning the concluſion. There was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing reſolued on at the firſt or ſecond ſitting, but at the third it was alwaies reſolutely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded what was to bee done: ſo that if any Conqueſt were determined, letters were written to the <hi>Alcaydes</hi> of the men of warre, directing them with ſuch companies of horſe and foot, as were vnder their command to repaire to ſuch place and quarter as was to them appointed. And other letters were ſent to the <hi>Alcaydes</hi> who were Gouernors of the Kingdomes, to prepare for them all kind of neceſſarie Prouiſion, as well by Sea as by Land. Touching the <hi>pay of theſe men of warre,</hi> he had alotted out of his Rents be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Tenths of Bread</hi> and other particular reuenues pertayning to his Royall Crowne, a ſufficient portion for the pay of euery <hi>Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of his men of warre; which went out with their <hi>Mayordomo Pagador, Treaſurer or Paymaſter,</hi> by which meanes he aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled great Armies, taking out of his Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie onely the Prouiſion for his Armie by Sea
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:181:21"/>and the pay of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> in his ſeruice. And in the <hi>In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> whiles the Armie was gathering together, the <hi>Alcayde</hi> who was Admirall of the Sea was bound to aſſemble his Nauie, to furniſh it wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h victuals and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neceſſaries, and to haue it readie rigged and prepared to embarke the men of warre at the day appointed. And the <hi>Alcayde</hi> who was Captaine Generall of the Army by Land was bound to cauſe the vneuen and ill paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the wayes and Prouinces which the Regiments of Souldiers were to paſſe, to bee made euen and paſſable for their ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h, to aſſemble the Armie, and to ſee it furniſhed with victuals and all neceſſaries. And as ſoone as the Armie was aſſembled and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banked, the Generall of the Armie by Land was bound to obey the <hi>Alcayde</hi> that was Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall by Sea, being on the Sea; and the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall of the Sea in like manner was to bee obedient to the Generall of the Armie by Land, when hee was on the Land, by which meanes hee preuented all diſſention and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate betwixt them. Heneuergaue them or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which they were preciſely to follow in proſecution of the warre, but left all to their
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:181:21"/>diſcretion; ſaying, that the proceeding of the warres could not in the houſe be directed, in ſuch ſort as they might in the Armie. And becauſe he euer choſe ſuch Generals as were of great wiſdome and experience in the art militarie, he neuer vndertooke any conqueſt againſt any King, whether he were a Moore, a Chriſtian, or Gentile, but hee preuailed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him.</p>
               <p>This King <hi>Jacob Almanſor</hi> had this quality that hee neuer beſtowed any place of an <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayde</hi> or Captaine on any that ſued for it, how well ſoeuer hee were qualified and fitted for the place: neither would he place him in any other office, if once he had made fute for any. Hee made choice of men experienced, who had ſerued him long both in peace and war, done ſome remarkeable ſeruices, by which they had approued their wiſdome and valour and the loue and loyalty with which they ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him. Hee had no reſpect of bloud or of high Linage, but if he were a priuate man of poore eſtate, and had valour to rule and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne, he would giue him the beſt and high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt place amongſt his Councellors. And if he were of great parentage, and had no va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:181:22"/>he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, nor would any way vſe his ſeruice. By <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>aſon of his good choyce when his Armies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> from their conqueſts, his Generals vſed to make him Relations of the notable things which euery of his Captaines, <hi>Alcaydes,</hi> or any priuate Souldiers had done, which he read, and (with out forgetting any) rewarded them and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred them to ſuch places and offices as hee found conuenient. And as none durſt make a lye vnto him; ſo had none any aduantage by fauour without merino in ſuch ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> that all endeuoured to ſerue him with g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critie, being well aſſured that their trauaile ſhould be rewarded according to the ſeruice they had done him. And this was the chiefe cauſe for which hee was ſo well ſerued and feared by all the Nations of the World.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:181:22"/>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the manner and order which he held in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement of his Kingdomes.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His King <hi>Almanſor</hi> vſed to ſpend the Monday on the care and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of his Kingdomes in ſuch ſort, that after the firſt houre of the day he entred into his Councel of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement with his foure Councellors of State, where they made him account of the affaires and notable accidents which the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caydes</hi> of Gouernment had written and certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, which if they were but ordinarie, were anſwered and decreed as was conuenient, it being the charge of the ancient Councellor to returne the anſwers, and make diſpatches, as it was alſo in the Councell of Warre. But if they were matters of Importance they gaue him a Memoriall or Bill thereof, that hee might take ſuch order as was fitting: for as concerning the Prouiſions of offices of <hi>Alcay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,</hi> and Gouernments, and other charges and miniſtrations, he diſtributed them him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, without aduice of Councellors. Then going out of his Councell, they placed a ſeat
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:181:23"/>for him in publicke, on which hee ſate, and gaue audience to ſuch as came to complaine of any Iniuſtice done by any of his Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, receiuing their Complaints and Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that hee might confider and redreſſe their grieuances, which he did very ſpeedily, vprightly, and with great ſeueritie. Albeit ſuch accidents ſeldome hapned, by reaſon that his Iuſtice was ſo feared, that no <hi>Alcayde</hi> or Gouernour durſt doe any Iniuſtice, that none might haue cauſe to complaine.</p>
               <p>Concerning Elections and choice of his officers and Miniſters, he carried himſelfe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this manner. Of all his <hi>Alcaydes</hi> and Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines that had ſerued in his warres, hee had particular notice and remembrance of the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of their perſons, and the notable ſeruices they had done, by the true Relations which his Generals had made him, as before is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed, which hee kept regiſtred ſummarily in a little booke, together with the place of their Birth, their Age, and how long they had ſerued. And when hee ſaw they were growne old and wearied in his ſeruice, hee licenſed them to take reſt, and honoured them with places and offices of Viceroyes of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:181:23"/>Kingdomes, <hi>Alcaydes,</hi> or Commanderies and Captainſhips of Caſtles and fortreſſes: Some alſo with Gouernments of Prouinces and Cities, giuing them good and honourable ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laries, receiuing ſtill their pay which they had in the warres. He obſerued alſo this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that hee gaue them alwaies theſe places of Preferment amongſt their friends &amp; kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the ſame Country where they were borne; neuer taking their offices from them nor changing them to other places, vnleſſe they had done ſome Iniuſtice, or committed ſome other fault: and then hee vſed firſt to take from them their offices; and then to cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſe them according to the qualitie of their offence, ſaying that hee that once did any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice for his particular Intereſt, no longer deſerued to bee a Iudge, not ſo much as a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The principall reaſon on which this King grounded for this election and diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution of his offices, was this. Hee ſaid that none could euer know the valour of men, and that naturall talent with which the Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne God and Nature had endowed them, except it were in the militarie Art; for therein the valiant are tryed, and their courage and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:181:24"/>wiſdome for Gouenment of Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weales in Peace and warre is diſcerned. There men diſcouer their good fortune in their deeds of Armes, in ouercomming great ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, in winning of rich ſpoiles, in preſeruing that place and Command which they haue gotten with ſo much trauaile and labour, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>during ſo many euil dayes and worſe nights, putting their life and honour in hazard, and in danger to loſe all in a moment. There men come acquainted with hunger and thirſt, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe and want, ſleeping on the ground, ſickneſſe, cold and heat, yea, with intolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble trauaile: with all which manifold expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience they becom in their Age full of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and skil how to rule &amp; gouerne Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monweales: for with that valor and courage with which they won their Honour and their wealth, with the ſame they preſerue the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon wealth in Peace, gouerning it with vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe obſeruing Iuſtice: and with thoſe neceſſities and miſeries which they haue paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed through in the courſe of their life they condole thoſe that are poore and miſerable, apt to relieue their miſerie and neceſſitie: and aboue all they which are couragious, valiant
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:181:24"/>zealous of their Law and Religion, louers of their King and country; and who with ſuch care and vigilancie wonne that Reward in the warre, that they deſerued to bee Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors of Kingdomes; with the ſame minde alſo would they gouerne the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, not being able to endure any Iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice or euill to be done.</p>
               <p>Hee neuer gaue any of their offices to any other priuate men, how wiſe and valiant ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, if they had not wonne Honour and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation by long ſeruice in the warres, and were alſo of ripe yeares and counſell, and had done ſome notable acts to reſtifie their wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, courage, valour, and abilitie, deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing offices, Adminiſtrations, and Gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Common-weales, Kingdomes and Prouinces; for hee ſaid <hi>that men brought vp in obſcuritie, and liuing in corners, had not the courage to aduenture and trye their fortune, but being cowardly and puſillanimous were euer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate; and that Fortune her ſelſe neuer fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them in any thing, but alwaies deſpiſed and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſteemed them,</hi> and that therefore he made no reckoning of ſuch for any employment, as hauing in them no valor, no naturall abilitie.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:181:25"/>
               <p>This King <hi>Iacob Almanſor</hi> was ſo vigilant in the Gouernment of his Kingdomes, that many times he went out by night, diſguiſed in the habit of a countryman or common-downe and toperſon, &amp; viſited the publicke places, romes, and offices in his court, and ſometimes in the habit of a merchant, hee would trauaile two or three dayes iourney: otherwhiles hee put on the habit of a Souldier, with two or three diſguiſes, when he would informe himſelfe of any notable thing; and how his Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours adminiſtred Iuſtice; and how his Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines and Generals carried themſelues in Peace and Warre, and ſo came to the verify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of what he ſought, with much diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and many times chaſtiſed the delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents when they were moſt ſecure. And this he did ſo oft, and ſo warily, that his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects tooke a Prouerbe or common ſpeech a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, which they often vſed in their aſſemblies and meetings, when any one ſpake of ought that was vnlawfull, the reſt would preſently reprehend him,<note place="margin">It is to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that in thoſe dayes the Arabians vſed to weare a vaile ouer their face.</note> ſaying, take heede leſt the King <hi>Iacob Almanſor</hi> heare you. For they thought he was in euery place, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee vſed in ſuch manner to goe vp and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:181:25"/>downe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and to doe ſuch notable deeds as cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed admiration; with which hee held all his Subiects in great ſeare and awe: and all the <hi>Alcaydes of Gouernment</hi> thought he was euer looking on them; ſo that they durſt not do any Iniuſtice, or neglect ought that was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their charge, knowing him to bee of ſo ſharpe and ſeuere diſpoſition, that if once they fell into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſgrace, they ſhould neuer hold vp their heads againe whiles they liued. This was the mayne cauſe that he gouerned all his Kingdomes in peace, and that none of his <hi>Alcaydes or Viceroyes</hi> durſt any wayes at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt the leaſt thing in the World.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the vertuous exerciſes, in which the King <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob Almanſor</hi> ſpent the Tueſdayes, and Wenſdayes.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His King (as wee haue rehearſed in the Diſtribution, which hee made of the dayes of the weeke) choſe the <hi>Tueſdayes</hi> and <hi>Wenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes</hi> for his perticular Exerciſes, which hee
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:181:26"/>diuided in this manner<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>The Tueſday</hi> mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his <hi>Huntſmen, Mountaynmen Bowmen,</hi> and other Seruants and Officers of that kind being aſſembled, he went out to the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, and there delighted and exerciſed himſelfe in chaſing and hunting all kind of game, both of Bird and Beaſts, of which he had great ſtore and varietie in the Woods, Groues, and Gardens of <hi>Hillan</hi> and <hi>Albaſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim,</hi> kept and ordered in the beſt manner that might be; where he recreated himſelfe with his followers; and to thoſe of them that had performed any notable exploit that day (wherein he much delighted) hee rewarded with ten pieces of Gold. This Exerciſe hee followed vntill noone; and then dined in the midſt of a great houſe of pleaſure which hee had there; where all that followed him did eate, and many poore folkes were refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed; for hee vſed that day and place, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for matters of Almes and reliefe of the poore, and would not by expreſſe order bee encombred therewith eſlewhere. When hee had dined, a <hi>Mayordomo</hi> put into a purſe a thouſand pieces of Gold, called <hi>Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ales,</hi> and then he ſitting downe in a ſquare Court,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:181:26"/>there came the poore before him, as well thoſe of his Court, as of other Townes and Cities, which brought euery one his Certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficate from his <hi>Alcayde</hi> or <hi>Gouernour</hi> of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of his neceſsities. And if it were for <hi>Mariage of poore Orphanes</hi> or other ſuch occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, he gaue direction for their reliefe. And it they were ſome ſmaller wants, hee ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed them preſently out of that purſe which his <hi>Mayordomo</hi> had filled. But if the matters were of more importance, he ſubſcribed his anſwere to thoſe Relations or Certificates of his Gouernours: giuing direction how eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one ſhould be relieued, and out of what receipt or reuenue, in ſuch good ſort, that all went away contented and ſatisfied, Hee ſaid to his followers, that hee eſteemed that the beſt day of his life, in which hee relieued all thoſe poore folkes for the loue of the ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne God. It was remarkable in him, that it could neuer be noted, that euer any ſought for almes or ſuccour at his hands, whether he were <hi>Moore, Chriſtian, or Iew,</hi> that went away vnrelieued. <hi>He held opinion that there was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer any King poore, and that if hee were ſo, hee ſhould bee very miſerable and vnfortunate: and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:181:27"/>that Kings ſhould be as large in giuing as they are in demanding and receiuing of their Subiects, without which they haue neyther power, Empire, nor command in the World, more then a priuate perſon.</hi> He was ſo readie to relieue the needy, and to ſuccour the ſuccourleſſe, that going one day on hunting, hee loſt himſelfe, being ſeuered from his Seruants; and holding on his courſe through the Wood, hee found a poore trauayling man, who being taken with ſome ſodaine ſickneſſe, was fallen on the ground vnable to goe any farther: he there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alighting, laid him on his owne horſe, and hauing tyed him faſt in his Saddle, hee took the reines of the bridle in his hands, and ſo walked on foote himſelfe more then two leagues before hee met with his traine: who albeit they offered to eaſe him of the care of the ſicke, and to mount him on another horſe, yet he would by no meanes yeeld vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, but conducted him with his owne hands, vntill hee had brought him to his houſe in the Wood; and there cauſed him to be cured, till hee was throughly recouered: and when being become ſound, hee kiſſed his hand at parting with many thankes as
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:181:27"/>was fitting for ſo great a auour, he anſwered, that there belonged no thankes vnto him, but that all was due to the Soueraigne God, who had ſent him that day to ſuccoun him; for he aſſured him by his Royall Crowne, that hee had loſt his company, wandering hee knew not where, nor which way he went, vntill he lighted happily on him in that place where hee found him ſicke: and that it could not poſſibly be, but that he was guided by God, ſeeing he wandered in that country in which hee was borne and bred, and yet neuer had the like befallen him. And when he that was healed would haue taken his leaue to depart, he commanded a good ſumme of money to be giuen him out of his Treaſurie, that hee might liue in good ſort, and ſo did diſmiſſe him. Theſe and other like things did the King <hi>Almanſor,</hi> that thoſe about him might learne and take good and laudable examples out of his manners and cuſtomes.</p>
               <p>The day following, being <hi>Wenſday,</hi> hee gaue no Audience, neyther treated with any; but ſhut himſelfe into his Chamber, repoſing himſelfe after his Hunting and violent exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing which hee had vſed the <hi>Tueſday</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:181:28"/>And there being alone, hee wrought <hi>Aſtrolabes of Aſrologie</hi> and other <hi>Inſtruments</hi> of great worth and high eſtimation amongſt the wiſe of his time. Otherwhiles hee made of <hi>inlayd warke</hi> ſuch delicate things, and of ſuch great account, that the skilfulleſt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and profeſſors of that Art tooke exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and patterne of thoſe pieces which hee had wrought: for in all theſe things hee had a ſingular dexteritie, ſubtiltie, and excell en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of hand. Hee made <hi>Croſſe-bowes</hi> alſo, and other kind of <hi>Weapons</hi> and <hi>Armes,</hi> eſpecially, <hi>Coates of Maile,</hi> of ſuch excellencie, that I can witneſſe that I ſaw one of them (which hee had giuen to an <hi>Ale ayde, being his Fauourite</hi>) ſold for the weight thereof in Siluer. In theſe Exerciſes hee vſed to ſpend theſe dayes, and not in any other ſort.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:181:28"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the Exerciſes which hee vſed on the Thurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, and how hee exerciſed the Sciences a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Learned.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His King <hi>Iacob Almanſor</hi> was ſo learned in all Sciences, and ſuch a louer of learned men of what facultie ſoeuer they were, that there neuer came any to his knowledge and acquaintance, but hee honoured and loued him exceedingly: and on the contrary, hee no leſſe hated and eſchewed the fooliſh and ignorant. <hi>For hee ſaid, that there was no greater miſerie in the World then Ignorance, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any Monſter how fierce, foule, or abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſoeuer that was comparable thereto.</hi> Hee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claymed ouer all his Kingdomes, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſhould bring him any Booke that were not in his <hi>Librarie</hi> alreadie, of what fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie ſoeuer it was, ſhould receiue double the value, according to the iuſt eſtimation thereof: and performed it accordingly. And if they were exquiſite Bookes and good, hee paid much more to them that brought them,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:181:29"/>giuing great rewards. By this meanes hee ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered ſuch a multitude of Books, that when he numbred them in his Library, hee found there <hi>fiftie fiue thouſand, ſeuen hundred twentie and two bodies of all kind of Sciences, in their ſeuerall Languages;</hi> and weighing them in a weight, they weighed <hi>twelue hundred and nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene Quintalls of Paper.</hi> And for verifying of this Truth,<note place="margin">A Quintall is taken for a hundred weight.</note> the greateſt part of them is yet at this preſent, remayning in the <hi>Librarie of the Royall Palace,</hi> which your Highneſſe at this day poſſeſſeth: and if any of the Bookes be wanting (whereof I make no doubt) the number and names of the Authors will bee found in the Catalogue, which this learned King cauſed to bee made. When <hi>Thurſday</hi> was come, hee went into a Royall Hall or large roome adioyning to his Librarie, which was adorned with rich hangings, and the floore couered with Carpets of great price, and the roome repleniſhed with coſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Seates, where by he honored thoſe learned men with whom he had treated &amp; conferred about matters of Learning; for hee would neuer permit any of them to ſtand nor heare him a word at thoſe times appointed for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:181:29"/>vntill they were all ſet downe on their Seates; Saying, that <hi>ſeeing Learning ought to bee honoured; ſo ought alſo the men that were learned, being the Sonnes of ſo honourable a Mother.</hi> Being thus aſſembled, one of them declared the <hi>Propoſitions</hi> which hee mayntay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in his facultie; the reſt arguing on the contrary. And if any doubt aroſe on the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legation of Authours, there ſtood alwayes readie at the doore of the <hi>Librarie,</hi> a learned man that had the cuſtodie thereof; who brought preſently the Book which the King called for, whereby the doubt was reſolued. This courſe hee commonly continued till noone, and then hee went to his dinner, and cauſed all thoſe learned men to dine in the ſame roome, and to bee ſerued as himſelfe. Dinner being ended, the King <hi>Iacob Alman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor</hi> went vnto them with many thankes for that good which hee acknowledged of them, commending their learning and knowledge, appointing them alſo <hi>what points</hi> they ſhould ſtudie againſt the next meeting, that they might be the better prepared to yeeld him a good reſolution; and named which of them ſhould mayntayne the <hi>Concluſion.</hi> Hauing
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:181:30"/>diſmiſſed them from his preſence: he entred his <hi>Library,</hi> and ſpent there the reſt of that day, ſtudied in what facultie hee moſt deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; for he was ſo great a Louer of Learning that whiles I ſerued him I heard him often ſay; <hi>That hee had no greater griefe in the world, then that the neceſſarie care of the Gouernment of his houſe and Kingdomes would allow him no more time but one day of the weeke for the getting of Learning; and that if it were lawfull for him to doe it without being noted of negligence, he would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer meddle of any other thing all the dayes of his life; and that hee neuer did any thing that grieued him more then the aceepting of the office of King, and taking on him the Rule and Gouernment of the Royall Scepter of his Kingdomes, in the life of his father</hi> Abilgualit, <hi>whereby he had loſt much time which he might freely haue employed in Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, without being troubled with the care of the Rule and Gouernment of the Common-wealth; and therefore often wiſhed that his Sonne wore of ripe age, of Mature Iudgement, and Counſell, that hee might leaue him his Royall Scepter, and rest from that great care which he had of the common good of his Subiects.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:181:30"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>In what manner he commanded the Sciences to be read in his Kingdomes, and of the Vniuer ſities and Colledges which he cauſed to bee built, and endowed with the Hospitalls for the ſicke and the poore.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O friendly was this King <hi>Iacob Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſor</hi> to Learning and to Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men, and ſo deſirous that the exerciſe of Learning, and the number of thoſe that were Learned might increaſe in his Kingdomes, that hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the building of the <hi>famous Collegiate Hospitall,</hi> which at this day is adioyning to his Royall Palace, and was by him endowed with a large and ample reuenue: wherein he alſo conſtituted Learned <hi>Profeſſors</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> in all Faculties, to reade and teach the Sciences with good Salaries: allowing alſo therein Prouiſion of Diet, Apparell, and Bookes for all the poore Students, without putting their Fathers and Friends to any charge, vntil they were Graduates: and there graciouſly gaue them the Titles of their
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:181:31"/>Degrees. This was done in the one ſide of this Hoſpitall: where hee eſtabliſhed <hi>ſeuen Academies.</hi> In the other ſide hee appointed a place for the poore diſeaſed where they were cured, as they are at this preſent, with ſuch ſeruice, regard, care, and diligence, as they are alſo at this day, which becauſe it is notorious, I will ſpeake no more of it in this briefe Treatiſe of his life. And th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> King <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſor</hi> entred ſometimes into this Hoſpitall by a falſe doore out of his Pallace and paſſed his time viſiting the ſicke, and comforting of them, obſeruing how they were vſed, and whether there were any negligence in the Officers thereof. And then he went into the <hi>Academies,</hi> to ſee the Students how they ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died, and commanded the Maſters there, that ſome of the beſt able ſhould rehearſe ſome notable things of thoſe which there they had learned, and reioyced exceedingly therein, and cauſed gifts to be giuen to them which contented him beſt, ſaying that thoſe poore diſeaſed, and thoſe Students were his Sonnes, and that he that cheriſhed and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted them, ought to account that hee cheriſhed and comforted his owne Royall
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:181:31"/>perſon. Hee commanded alſo that other <hi>Hospitalls</hi> ſhould be builded in all the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Cities at his charge through out all his Kingdomes, for the like purpoſe, and gaue order to his <hi>Alcaydes</hi> who were Gouernours that they ſhould viſit them with the like care and diligence as he viſited thoſe of his Court. He gaue direction alſo that theſe <hi>Hospitalls</hi> ſhould receiue all Pilgrimes and Paſſengers of all Nations whatſoeuer, whether they were poore or rich, giuing them entertaynment both for Dyet and Lodging in conuenient ſort for themſelues, their Seruants, and the Beaſts which they rode on by the ſpace of ſix dayes: and that if they were poore, they ſhould giue them at their departure, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to defray their firſt dayes Iourney. There was euery yeare giuen him a Bill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning the Examination of the Students that were brought vp in the <hi>Hospitall</hi> of his Court, and of the others through out his Kingdomes, and of the abilitie and Talent of euery one; and for what employment hee was fitteſt. As alſo there was yearely giuen him a Note of the Offices that were voide, eyther of the <hi>Alfaquies</hi> of the <hi>Meſquitas,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:181:32"/>his Churchmen, or of the <hi>Cadies</hi> or Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Cities: and at Eaſter hee ſupplyed them, beſtowing them all himſelfe on whom he thought good. And ſo the Offices which became voide in thoſe <hi>Hospitalls,</hi> as well of the Maſters, Profeſſors, as of other Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters which held there any charge or place of eſteeme, hee alwayes preferred the Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents which had beene bred and brought vp there; and commanded the like to bee done by the Gouernours of his other King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes. By this good worke hee cured ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their Infirmities, augmented much the Sciences, and holpe many poore Students to ſtudie, free from care, by his good prouiding to relieue their neceſſities: which made them all pray to God for his health and long life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:181:32"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of his great Deeds and Battayles wonne by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe perſonally preſent; and by his Captaynes; and how he came to be called <hi>Almanſor.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>L the Exerciſes and the diuiſion of the Weeke, whereof wee haue hitherto intreated were done by the King <hi>Iacob Almanſor,</hi> when he was in his Royall Palace, and in his Court in Peace. But when he had any neceſſarie occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to trauell, or any war in hand which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired his perſonall Preſence, he left the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer charge and care to bee ſupplyed by one of his <hi>faucured Alcaydes,</hi> being a man of ſuch Learning, Experience, and abilitie as was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite: in ſuch ſort that there was no default, were his abſence neuer ſo long. And albeit he neuer embarkt himſelfe to make warre by Sea on any King, but did all by his <hi>Generalls</hi> and <hi>Alcaydes</hi> of his men of Warre: yet when he intended to winne and conquer any king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome or Prouince by land, he delighted ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly to bee preſent in perſon with his Armie. For hee ſaid, that the vigour of his
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:181:33"/>ſpirit alone, and the onely imagining of his <hi>Alcaydes,</hi> Captaynes, and Souldiers that hee was perſonally preſent, and that he aduentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his life as well as they, was ſufficient to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome many Enemies, and made them with redoubled courage to doe their endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour. In this manner, <hi>hee wonne thirteene ſet Battailes in the field, and tooke fiue Kings of the Gentiles,</hi> without being defeated in any of them, or his Armie routed: and euen with a few Souldiers, in regard of thoſe that came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, he performed great Exploits. The moſt notable was, that when hee had ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come one of the Kings of the Gentiles in the Country of <hi>Deuque,</hi> called <hi>Abni Raquib,</hi> and an Armie of ſeuentie thouſand foote, and foure thouſand horſe, which King eſcaped by flight, and met with a <hi>Sonne in Law</hi> of his named <hi>Abenyuſael Salami,</hi> who came to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour him, whereupon receiuing new cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, hee turned againe to ſee whether hee could recouer what hee had loſt, and bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenged of his enemy. And albeit hee came againſt him with freſh Souldiers that were not wearied, which were no fewer then forty thouſand foot, and two thouſand horſe: and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:181:33"/>the Armie of the King <hi>Almanſor</hi> was now wearied and enfeebled, many hauing beene hurt and ſlaine in the former battaile, and he being much perplexed: yet ſeeing he could not now retire, but with great loſſe and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduantage, nor without ſome imputation of cowardiſe, he reſolued to abide his enemies encounter anew: and to re-enforce his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, he went euery where himſelfe, putting them in order, and encouraging of them, ſaying alowde after this manner; <hi>Good Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers and valiant Warriours, let vs dye with Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour like Conquerors and victorious, as wee are at this preſent; and let vs not flye diſhonourably; for J will bee the firſt that ſhall ſet vpon the enemie; and bee yee not afraid ſince</hi> Abilgualit. Alman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor <hi>is with you, whom the Souereigne God hath neuer yet ſuffered to be euercome; no more ſhall be at that time.</hi> With theſe words hee began the Battaile without farther ſpeech; and he fought valiantly himſelfe in his Royall perſon, killed many, and tooke the King <hi>Abni Raquib:</hi> and his Sonne in Law dyed fighting in that Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile brauely. And when they had taken the ſpoyle of his Campe, all his Souldiers ſaid that the higheſt God had made <hi>Abilgualit</hi> vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:181:34"/>and that with great reaſon he might be called <hi>Almanſor.</hi> And from that day for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, they named him <hi>Almanſor Abenforoh,</hi> whereas before he was called <hi>Abilgualit Iacob Abninacer;</hi> albeit in all theſe Chapters which I haue written of his life, I haue alwayes na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med him <hi>Almanſor,</hi> that I might not alter his name which was beſt knowne: and he might well be ſo called, becauſe he was neuer ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come in any battaile, nor any of his Generals in any warres or battailes, which they fought or made by his direction, eyther by Sea or by Land, which are all regiſtred in the Booke which is written of his life and warres of his time, and of his great Exploits, and thoſe of his <hi>Alcaydes</hi> and Gouernours of his Armies: with which I intend not to cloy the Readers. But will only rehearſe the number of them, which were <hi>ſeuentie and three Battailes, or foughten Fields by Land, and thirteene fights by Sea.</hi> Touching the diuiding of the Spoyles which his Souldiers had when the Battailes were ended, he commanded all to be gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and laid together in ſuch ſort, that none durſt take any thing without his leaue. And the diſtributio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of them was made according
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:181:34"/>to his Statutes and Ordinances for the wars; which was, <hi>that euery Souldier which was ſlaine in the Warre ſhould haue his part and portion as farre forth as they that were liuing: and ſuch parts and portions were accordingly deliuered to the companions and friends of the dead who vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertooke the deliuering of them to the Children, Wiues, and Heires of them to: whom they belonged. For he ſaid it was not iuſt nor reaſonable, that hee who dyed fighting ſhould loſe his part, ſeeing they that were his had loſſe enough in loſing of him without loſing the goods, which were gotten with the price of his life.</hi> When hee had made this diſtribution, he vſed to giue audience to any that was grieued therewith, giuing order briefly, and ſummarily in what manner hee ſhould be righted, in ſuch ſort that they were all ſatisfied and well contented. And this was the chiefe cauſe that when hee intended any warre he was ſo ſought to, and ſerued by his followers, who were readie to hazard their liues for him without feare.</p>
               <p>This King <hi>Iacob Alnanſor</hi> as hee was very louing to the <hi>Learned,</hi> and friendly to the <hi>valiant</hi> and <hi>vertuous,</hi> ſo was hee as aduerſe an enemy to <hi>Lyers, Pratlers,</hi> and <hi>Gamesters,</hi> and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:181:35"/>abhorred and loathed the <hi>Loytering <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrifts and Idlers:</hi> for he ſaid that all ſueh per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons were vnprofitable to the Common-weales; like the Droues in the Bee-hiues, that are no wayes helpfull to the Bees, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in gathering nor preſeruing the Honie or the Waxe; but only to fill vp the roomes in their houſes; and to eate and conſume what they had prouided for their ſuſtenance: and theſe hee vſed to chaſten according to their deſert. He would neuer be idle ſo much as a moment; but was euer buſied in good and vertuous Exerciſes. <hi>He cauſed alſo a Law to be made, that what perſon ſoeuer hee were that had no Office, Trade, or courſe of life wherein to employ his time, ſhould be held infamous and of no reputation, of what eſtate or degree ſoeuer hee were:</hi> which was the cauſe that in imitation of him all his Subiects ſhunned idleneſſe, and beſtowed their time in vertuous Exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: by meanes whereof they eſcaped many vices and diſeaſes, and liued without want, except it were here and there one, as it is in all Kingdomes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:181:35"/>
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How the reſigned his Royall Scepter to his eldeſt Sonne; and of his retiredneſſe which he choſe, and of a Letter written to his Sonne of Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions, for his good Gouernment whereunto hee was bound.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He King <hi>Abilgualit Iacob Alman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor,</hi> ſeeing him ſelfe waxen old and wearie of his Gouernment, and conſidering that his Sonne <hi>Abil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gualis Abninace</hi> was of ſufficient age, wit and abilitie to rule and gouerne, reſigned vnto him his Royall Scepter, his Crowne and Kingdomes, with the conſent of his wiſeſt Counſellours and the <hi>Alcaydes</hi> that were Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours: retyring himſelfe to a ſolitarie life in that Country houſe in the Mountaynes of <hi>Albaſatim</hi> and <hi>Alhillan</hi> which hath beene before mentioned: where on the top of a high Rocke neere adioyning, hee had cauſed to be built a ſumptuous <hi>Mezquita</hi> or <hi>Temple,</hi> with a <hi>Colledge</hi> or <hi>Monaſterie,</hi> wherein might liue an <hi>Heremite</hi> or <hi>Abbot,</hi> with <hi>fortie Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples or Monkes,</hi> appointing to bee chiefe Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour therein, a man of much Learning
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:181:36"/>named <hi>Mahomet el Gazeli.</hi> In this man hee had ſuch confidence that hee conſulted with him concerning his weightieſt affaires and matters of moſt importance, as with a man of Learning and Wiſdome, who gaue him ſound aduice, and of whom he had learned much. To that houſe therefore among thoſe woodie Mountaines, he withdrew himſelfe, there hence often repayring to that <hi>Mezqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> and Monaſterie, to recreate himſelfe in conference and couerſation with <hi>Mahomet el Gazeli:</hi> not permitting any to viſit him but his Seruants and his ancient <hi>Alcaydes,</hi> neither them for their pleaſure or paſtime; for if they came not on ſome buſineſſe of importance or earneſt occaſion, he admitted them not to his preſence, neither ſuffered them to viſit him. In this manner hee paſſed his life with great quietneſſe and freedome from cares.</p>
               <p>Hee very cunningly and ſubtilly vſed to examine ſuch of his ancient Seruants and <hi>Alcaydes</hi> as came vnto him, euery of them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part by himſelfe, and that very particularly, in what manner his Sonne <hi>Abilgualit Abni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace</hi> gouerned his Kingdomes; whether his Subiects ſpake well of him, &amp; whether they
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:181:36"/>complayned or miſliked him on iuſt cauſe or otherwiſe: with ſuch diligence he learned out of all of them what faults they found and obſerued in him. And this King <hi>Almanſor</hi> being zealous of the common good of his Kingdomes, and deſirous that his Sonne ſhould rule well, intending to reprehend him of ſome things, and inſtruct him how hee ſhould gouerne without reciting or mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning any one particular caſe of any that had complayned to him, wrote this Letter vnto him, which for the good admonitions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in contayned, I haue thought fit heere to ſet downe.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>The Letter of King <hi>Almanſor.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>PRayſe bee giuen to the Souereigne God, to whom Sacrifice and Prayer belongeth. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi> And his plenteous bleſsing and Grace come vpon you my Sonne; for without it no crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of his can doe any good thing, be it neuer ſo little, ſeeing all that is good commeth of his hand. This being thus premiſed, I haue thought good by this Letter to aduertize you of ſome things which
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:181:37"/>you are to obſerue co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>erning the Gouernment of your Kingdoms, that your Subiects may enioy much peace with ſafetie and tranquillitie; and that alſo you may be duely reuerenced, loued and feared of them, as is conuenient.</p>
                     <p>The firſt that you are to take care of is, that you be not proud, high-minded, nor preſumptuous, imagining diuers imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, becauſe you ſee your ſelfe made Lord of ſo many and ſo great King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and Armies by Sea and by Land, ſo many valorous <hi>Alcaydes</hi> and Captaines humbled in your Royall preſence, obedient to all your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and readie to execute whatſoeuer you ſhall appoint. To free your ſelfe from this great Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, you are to conſider the infinite power and euerlaſting Kingdom of God, hauing no beginning, middle, nor end, being of incomprehenſible power and wiſdome. And therewithall you are to conſider that your Kingdome is not infinite, but hath his limits and bounds; and is to finiſh, and to haue an end; as alſo the very memory of it among men. With this conſideration you ſhall bee in ſuch ſort humbled, as is requiſite you ſhould.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, you ought to conſider that the Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne God created you in this World, and gaue you power as a ſecond cauſe of his to fulfill his moſt
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:181:37"/>holy will in the Gouernment of his creatures heere on earth, by mayntayning Iuſtice and vſing Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and Clemencie, imitating your Creatour: and not to erre in the administration of this Office, you ought to behold and contemplate the Booke of this faire Theatre, called the World; this ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination of naturall Cauſes; this regular and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall mouing of the Heauens, Signes, and Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets: ſo many Generations and corruptions in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable men; and in all other things created in the Earth, in the Water, and in the Aire: the Night and the Day, the Raine, Haile and Wind, the changes of Times; Heate and Cold, and other alterations innumerable, being all created in ſuch orderly diſpoſition, with ſuch Wiſdome, perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Prouidence, as the wiſeſt and skilfulleſt could neuer attaine to know: and how from the time in which hee created this goodly Frame to this preſent, and to the laſt inſtant in which it ſhall pleaſe him that it ceaſe and haue end, it neither hath beene nor ſhalbe needfull to adde or take any thing to it or from it: for that were to ſuppoſe ſome imperfection in his Workes, which cannot bee becauſe he is the God of higheſt perfection. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer to conſider how hee ſuſtayneth it, gouerning and maintayning all things with Iudgement and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:181:38"/>Mercy, with great and wonderfull Prouiden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>; ſuch a one he is. You ought therefore to perceiue that your Gouernment is Diſorder; your Iuſtice Jniuſtice; your Mercie is want of Clemencie, your Charitie Couetouſneſſe, your carefull Diligence is Slothfulneſſe; and to conclude, that all your Knowledge is but Ignorance. And I can aſſure you, that if you would be mercifull to his Creatures; yet you cannot pardon their ſinnes; If you bee a good Iusticer, you can onely chaſten their bodies, not their Soules. If neuer ſo charitable, you cannot giue a bleſsing to their goods: If you bee large and louing, yet you cannot make them liue foreuer: If you incline to giue them caſe and reſt, yet you cannot giue them glorie: If you deſire to adde comfort to them, yet you can giue them no true and perfect conſolation of Spirit. Behold, therefore what I ſay vnto, you that you may know how great is the miſerie of man: Seeing that with all your power and Kingdomes you cannot make one drop of water to fall out of the Region of the Cloudes; nor make one leaſe of a Palmotree; nor yet deliuer and free your ſelfe from the leaſt tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation of the World.</p>
                     <p>The third thing which you are to call to mind, is that you muſt die, and muſt be iudged by our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereigne
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:181:38"/>God with a ſtrict account of the good and euill you haue done in this life; like a ſinfull miſerable man; and that ouer and aboue this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count which is to bee giuen by all men in generall. Kings are to yeeld another particular to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, which is, whether they haue well adminiſtred and gouerned their Common-weales. If only in regard of their Kingly power they haue dealt hardly with their Subiects without any iuſt cauſe or offence of theirs: If they haue impoſed great payments, or exacted vnneceſſarie Tributes; If they haue done wrong or vniuſtly for their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular intereſt; if they did not condole with the poore, and relieue and eaſe the oppreſſed, hauing power to remedie their diſtreſſe, and to redreſſe their grieuances: and to conclude, if they haue beene careleſſe of the good of their Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weales; Woe bee to the Soules of ſuch; for they ſhall be condemned to perpetuall torments. By this you may cleerely ſee that you and your King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes are nothing, and haue no being whereof to make any reckoning. I aſſure you therefore, that if you had duely conſidered the charge and dutie whereunto you bound your ſelfe that day on which I reſigned the Gouernment into your hands, that you had more cauſe to mourne and to be ſorrowfull
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:181:39"/>then to ordaine Feaſts and Triumphs with Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke and Disports, which in effect were vſed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as is vſually accustomed. Let theſe things but paſſe through your memorie and clearer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and then Pride and Ambition will fall vnder your feet and you ſhall eaſily, ſubdue them. For I aſſure you, <hi>that one dramme of Pride will weigh heauier then one hundred Quintals of good vnderſtanding in the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt man in the World:</hi> and ſee; it is the verie gate by which the Deuill the accurſed of God entreth to tempt men; and ouercommeth, capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uateth and ouerthroweth them into the fearefull, horrible, euerlaſting Hell: from which the Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne God for his great Mercie free vs and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The fourth thing of which I admoniſh you is, that you yeeld Juſtice, adminiſtring it indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to all that ſhall aske it; for I aſſure you, that the King which ſhall not ſo administer it will ſoone be dispoſſeſſed of his Kingdome as a man vnworthy to reigne: <hi>For God permitteth vnbeleeuing in this World, reſeruing the chaſtiſement thereof for the day of his finall Iudgement, and maintaineth the World, and all his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures with Iuſtice and Mercie; albeit ſome
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:181:39"/>are without the true knowledge of him; but he readily chaſtiſeth with rigour, euen in this life, vniuſtice and wickedneſſe, when malice increaſeth, and men are obſtinate therein like a Iuſt Iudge as he is.</hi> Be no teller of <hi>Lies,</hi> for it is the baſeſt thing in the World, and the Lier is the Deuils Diſciple, a man without Vertue a Traitour to the Truth and an enemy therof, &amp; one to whom no credit is to be giuen; &amp; the leaſt puniſhment that men allot him is, that although he ſpeake the truth yet he is not beleeued. Let your <hi>Speech</hi> be mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, that men may not note you for a Pratler; which would make you vnregarded, and held for a man of little diſcretion. All theſe good aduertiſements in my Letter haue their contraries, and therefore our Souereigne God gaue you freedome of will, and liberty of choice that you might follow the good and of chew the euill; and without his helpe you can doe nothing. This only I will warne you, that you ſet God before you in all your waies, doing Iuſtice with charity, ſimplicitie, and vprightneſſe, and you ſhall not erre, whatſoeuer you take in hand. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I might write much more in this Letter; Yet this may ſuffice, for there is included in it what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer can bee required of him that will well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of it to put it in practice, as I intend it, to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:181:40"/>his intire ſatisfaction which I doubt not but you will performe with the helpe of our Souereigne God his bleſsing and grace; whom I humbly pray and beſeech to grant it you as I giue you mine; and haue you in his keeping. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>From this houſe of <hi>Albaſatin,</hi> 
                           <date>the twentieth day of <hi>Rageb</hi> in the ninetie and fixth yeere.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <hi>This Letter being receiued by the King</hi> Abilgualit, <hi>made him reioyce exceedingly, &amp; he tooke ſo earneſtly to heart this his Fathers reprehenſion, and put his Rules in practice in ſuch ſort, that he cauſed them that ſerued him to admire; for hee endeauoured with great care and diligence to amend the faults and negligences which hee had committed, eſpecially in adminiſtring Iuſtice, and began to follow the footſteps: of the King</hi> Alman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor <hi>his Father in his manner of Gouernment, and in all the reſt that hee vſed whiles hee raigned, in ſo much that in very ſhort time he made them ſee the amendement hee had made of his Life and Gouernment, in ſuch ſort that all his</hi> Alcaydes <hi>were much conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted therewith, though in ſome particular di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſted: for in all other things he could imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate his Father, ſauing only in his</hi> Liberalitie
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:181:40"/>
                  <hi>and</hi> Charitie; <hi>ſodim theſe the King</hi> Almanſor <hi>did much exceed him. And this I beleeue was the chiefe cauſe that hee neuer got ſo good a name as his Father.</hi> For certainly, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beralitie is a great vertue in Kings, wherewith they draw the minds of men to loue and ſerue them vnfaynedly with claritie: who on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie when they feele not their own intereſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, let fall the wings of their courage and cheerefulneſſe, louing and ſeruing more coldly and faintly: becauſe the iraſcible facultie hauing her reſidence as ſhe hath in the heart, and louing to be honoured and esteemed, and deſirous to haue her trauailes gratified with ſelfe proper intereſt, when that ceaſſeth, the working of the will doth ceaſſe. Especially in men of the Sword, which of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are moſt neceſſarie for Kings, as well for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing their Eſtates, as for the conquering of new Kingdomes and Signiories. <hi>Which was the chiefe cauſe that this King</hi> Abilgualit <hi>could neuer get any new Prouinces, but with much difficultie preſerued that Kingdome which he had inherited from his Father, and was at the point to haue loſt all for want of being free and generous towards his men of warre as was requiſite for their encouragement; for
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:181:41"/>they being accuſtomed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſuch gratification and largeſſe, as the King</hi> Iacob Almanſor <hi>vſed towards them, grew ſoone diſtaſted with the contrarie in his Sonne</hi> Abilgualit: <hi>which was the cauſe that he could neuer rayſe any Army by Land or by Sea worth the ſpeaking of, to doe any ſeruice of account, which merited the remembrance of Hiſtories. This may ſuffice for this particular; ſeeing my purpoſe is onely to write the life of the King</hi> Iacob Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſor.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How King <hi>Iacob Almanſor</hi> became ſicke to to Death; and how he aſſembled his wiſemen and the reſt of the <hi>Alcaydes;</hi> Of his prudent ſpeech hee made them; and the Pardon hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of them.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He King <hi>Almanſor</hi> ſpending his time quietly in that houſe of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bazatin</hi> and <hi>Albillan</hi> in company of <hi>Mahomet Algazeli</hi> and his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, after ſome time fell ſicke of an infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie of long continuance: and ſeeing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:181:41"/>to weare away, and that all the reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies which his Phyſicians applyed profited little: one day when they were about him in conſultation concerning his Diſeaſe, and the difficultie of the Cure, by reaſon of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold Syntomes, his great age and debilitie of Nature conſidered; hee ſaid thus vnto them; <hi>Yee, my Phyſicians, endeauour and labour to restore my health, but if Gods pleaſure be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; your purpoſe is but vaine. For I aſſure you, that when God hath determined to end a mans life, the Medicines miniſtred by the Phyſicians doe little auaile him; but ſerue rather to the haſtening his end. And ſo doe I conceiue, of thoſe which yee haue hitherto applyed vnto me, I lay no blame on you, but commend your Learning and Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; and that good affection wherewith you haue endeauoured to recouer my health: for which I thanke you, and eſteeme as much of your ſeruice as if you had preuailed. But I will not ſuffer you to be any longer deceiued; for the firſt day that I fell into this infirmitie, I aſſured my ſelfe, it would be my death knowing the ſame to bee a lingring ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Diſeaſe, differing from the reſt which I haue endured in the courſe of my life. And espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſeeing in the periods thereof I find it rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:181:42"/>it ſeemeth to me to be but loſſe of time to treat of recouery. Hence-forward therefore let no more paines be taken in that behalfe. For I am very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to the will of our Souereigne God; and do giue him infinite thankes for this great fauour which he vouchſafeth me, in taking me out of the troubles and calamities of this miſerable life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then hee cauſed the King <hi>Abilgualit,</hi> and the Infant <hi>Abraham Alamzari</hi> to bee called; who being come before him on their knees, and halfe proſtrate on the ground; kiſſed his hand; and he giuing them his bleſſing, ſaid thus vnto them. <hi>My deare and welbeloued Sonnes, the laſt period of my life is now at hand; the Souereigne God being pleaſed to take mee out of this World. That which I admoniſh you is, that yee loue like true Brethren, holding good confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie in your minds, and confirming it with good deeds; for ſo ſhall yee liue in Peace, and no enemie ſhall bee able to hurt you. And if yee continue not in Peace and good conformitie, yee ſhall ſoone ſee your Kingdomes ouerthrowne.</hi> And turning his eyes to the Infant <hi>Abraham,</hi> he ſaid thus; <hi>And you Sonne</hi> Abraham <hi>on paine of my curſe I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand you that you be alwaies obedient to the King</hi> Abilgualit <hi>your brother, and hold him hence-for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:181:42"/>in my place for your true Father and Lord; for I am confident in his wiſdome and vertue, that he will hold and vſe, and regard you as his Sonne.</hi> Then directing his eyes to his Sonne <hi>Abilgua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit</hi> hee ſaid, <hi>And ſo I command and charge you Sonne</hi> Abilgualit <hi>on like paine. And they lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and weeping in ſuch ſort that they could ſcarce ſpeake, anſwered, that they would obey him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then he called in his <hi>Alcaydes,</hi> the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of his Kingdomes; thoſe of his higheſt Councels, and the men of wiſdome and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, who attended in the vtter chamber; &amp; the reſt of his kinſmen &amp; friends, who when they had ſaluted him and kiſſed his hand, he commanded his <hi>Morabito Mahomet Algazeli</hi> (who being his fauorite, ſate at his beds head with the helpe of other attendants to lift him out of his bed: and ſitting, ſpake thus vnto them, <hi>My beloued Sonnes and true Friend in our Soueraigne God, The time is now come, in which my Soule is to paſſe out of this miſerable world, to yeeld account of the good and euill which I haue done in this life. I haue beene King and Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of theſe Kingdomes, and haue bred you, taught you, cheriſhed, and loued you as a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:181:43"/>and haue alſo chaſtened your exceſſes, and ouer-bold attempts with zeale and deſire to doe that which was requiſite. But being a man I know that in all things I haue erred as a man; for wee are all weake and miſerable Sinners. I therefore earneſtly intreate and beſeech you with all humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that if I be any way indebted to any of you, that yee preſently declare it: and that I may cauſe him to bee recompenced. And if there be none; I aske pardon of you all in generall of that which is past: for I, for my part, doe pardon and forgiue what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer in word or deed is by mee to bee, pardoned of any errours or neglects of yours, which you haue committed againſt mee. And this only I lay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you, that hee which vſeth not Mercie towards his Neighbour, muſt expect none at Gods hands at the laſt judgement.</hi> Which when they had heard, ſo great was the griefe they all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, and ſuch plentie of teares in their eyes, that they could not anſwer a word for a good ſpace, conſidering that by loſing their King <hi>Iacob Almanſor,</hi> they loſt their chiefeſt good, ſo great was the loue which they bore him. Yet after awhile they anſwered, that they all did pardon him, and if need were, would giue all their goods, and aduenture
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:181:43"/>their liues for him: If hee were ſo pleaſed to command, as readily as they or any of their Anceſtors had formerly done for his ſeruice, and that hee ſhould no way doubt of their pardon and promiſe, ſince they were there preſent to fulfill it. Then the King <hi>Almanſor</hi> could not refraine weeping, yet rendred great thankes for their louing offer, and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them: worning them alſo, that neither they nor any other Friends of his ſhould faile to be preſent at his buriall, for in their loue hee receiued great conſolation. Which they all promiſed, and departed from his preſeſence ſo afflicted and ſorrowfull that they ſhut vp themſelues; in ſuch ſort that in three dayes there was no Councell held, nor any buſineſſe diſpatched in Court vntill he ſomewhat amended: and then they ſell to negotiating and diſpatching affaires; yet with griefe and ſorrow for their good King, as they had great reaſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:181:44"/>
               <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How the King <hi>Iacob Almanſor</hi> dyed: Of his ſumptuous Enterment; his Tombe and Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and of the Epitaphes ingrauen on his Sepulchre.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He amendement of the King <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob Almanſor</hi> was not ſuch, as out of which any certaine ſigne of Recouery could be had: but it was rather a ſpace for the Indication of the laſt Parociſme of Death during this Interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. So that albeit his Seruants were in ſome hope, the good King being well aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of his death, neglected no moment nor minute for the diſpoſing of all things as hee held himſelfe bound. Hee willed all his moueable goods and monies to be giuen to the poore for Gods ſake: which were forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with diſtributed accordingly Then he gaue libertie to all his Slaues and Bondmen. Hee reſerued nothing but only his <hi>Librarie,</hi> charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the King <hi>Abilgualit</hi> he ſhould keepe it for himſelfe; and eſteeme it as it deſerued: and <hi>that in lieu thereof hee ſhould place in marriage
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:181:44"/>a thouſand poore Orphans, gining to euery of them a thouſand Miticales in marriage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the fift day after hee died naturally; leauing this preſent life on Thurſday, in the laſt watch of the night, on the third day of the Moone <hi>Rageb;</hi> in the <hi>hundred and ſecond yeare of the Hixera.</hi> On the day following,<note place="margin">This yeare in about the yeare of our Redemption 723.</note> the King <hi>Abilgualit</hi> wrote vnto all the <hi>Alcay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> of his Kingdomes a Letter to this effect, that they all ſhould mourne and ſolemnize his Funerall, Prayſe bee giuen to the Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne God. <hi>Amen.</hi> Hereupon they gaue or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for his Enterment, for which the King <hi>Iacob Almanſor</hi> had prepared and framed on the top of a high Hill, on the Southſide of that Houſe called <hi>Albazatin</hi> that ſumptuous <hi>Hermitage</hi> which is there ſeene at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and adioyning to it his Sepulchre, being a <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ault</hi> made of a rich kind of Iaſper of ſuch largeneſſe, as would containe fortie perſons, and vpon it cauſed a ſolid ſtone to be erected on foure Pillars of Alablaſter, and on the ſides foure ſmooth ſtones with his <hi>Epitaphs</hi> written in them in the greater Arabicke ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, with a very faire Character. This Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre is about a mile diſtant from the Houſe
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:181:45"/>of <hi>Albazatin.</hi> There were aſſembled at his Funerall fifteene hundred <hi>Alfaqui</hi> or princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Prieſts with the <hi>Alfaqui Mayor</hi> of the <hi>Mezquita</hi> of his Court, and the <hi>Morabito Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometo Algazeli</hi> with all his Monkes or Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and the King <hi>Abilgualit</hi> and the <hi>Infant Abraham,</hi> his Brother with all their Seruants; the <hi>Alcaydes</hi> that were Gouernours and thoſe of the <hi>Supreme Councels</hi> with their <hi>Preſidents,</hi> and all the other <hi>Alcaydes</hi> of the Court, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Peace or of Warre, which were <hi>twelue hundred</hi> in number: The common people being there innumerable, for there was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt none but would bee preſent at this So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnitie. All theſe Courtiers and <hi>Alfaqui</hi> were clad in mourning garments trayling their Royall Enſignes and Standards on the ground. That which was moſt to be noted, was the abundance of teares flowing from them, and the great mourning and lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they all made that day, eſpecially when they ſaw their good King laid in his Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre, and the entrance thereof cloſed, and faſt mured vp with ſtone, hauing no farther hope to ſee him any more. Prayſed bee God. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi> For the good which commeth to vs by
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:181:45"/>his hand. And thus ended this good King, leaning an eternall memorie of himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe that ſhould come after.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Epitaphs</hi> on his Sepulchre were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by <hi>Mahomet Algazeli:</hi> and are theſe that follow.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div n="1" type="epitaph">
                           <head>The firſt <hi>Epitaph.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>
                              <hi>HEere lyeth buried the high and highly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerenced King of moſt Noble Birth, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Race and Linage,</hi> deſcended of eightie and two Kings, Abilgualit Mirama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molin Iacob Almanfor: <hi>who was worthily cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi> the Conquerour, <hi>being neuer ouercome; the famouſeſt of the Sonnes of</hi> Naſts Abu Malique: <hi>Seeing</hi> hee wonne eightie and ſixe Battailes by Sea and by Land; <hi>and tooke fiue Kings; ſubdued three parts of the World,</hi> Aſia, Africke, <hi>and</hi> Europe; <hi>and gaue Peace and Tranquilitie to his Subiects: obſeruing Iuſtice with benignitie, and mercie. This is he that vſed Charitie, and aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented his Religion:</hi> hauing at his owne coſt builded in his Kingdomes fiue hundred and ſixe principall Mezquitas; eightie and two Hoſpitals; with as many Royall Colledges;
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:181:46"/>and endowed them with large and ſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous reuenues. This is hee that married euerie yeere at his charge a thouſand Orphanes, <hi>he that baniſhed Jgnorance and imbraced Learning. He that gaue to all the World examples of life in his Sayings and Sentences and notable Deeds of Armes. Hee who was an example of good and laudable cuſtomes. He that killed the hunger, and thirſt, and nakedneſſe of his Subiects with his large and liberall hands. Let immortall fame euer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                                    <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                                 </gap> on this Sepulchre, and acknowledge him that<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>l yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                                    <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                                 </gap> therein for her King and Lord, ſeeing by him ſhe is made triumphant, and victorious ouer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                                    <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                                 </gap>. This great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                                    <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                                 </gap> dyed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                                    <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                                 </gap> in his Inuocation of the Name of the mercifull God the Creatour of Heauen and Earth without ceaſing ſo much at a moment vntill his laſt gaspe imploring his incomprehenſible mercie, and fearing his high justice the third day of the Moone of</hi> Rageb, <hi>the night before Fryday,<note place="margin">This agreeth with the ſaid yeare of 723.</note> after the laſt watch in the hundred and ſecond yeare of the</hi> Hixera. <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed bee God and bleſſed bee his moſt holy Name for euer.</hi> Amen.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div n="2" type="epitaph">
                           <pb n="75" facs="tcp:181:46"/>
                           <head>The ſecond <hi>Epitaph.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>O How great is the Miſerie of men which hath brought a King of ſo great Power, Empire and Command to the eſtate wherein hee is at this preſent, who as yeſterday was honoured, reuerenced, and beloued of his people; and is now for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten and forſaken of them all: and remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſolitarie in the darke Caues of the earth. He which was wont to bee clad in Silke and Cloth of Gold and Siluer, and to ſleepe in the ſofteſt and ſweeteſt beds, curiouſly and richly decked and adorned; lyeth heere bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in the hard earth. He which vſed to goe perſumed with Muske and Amber, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther excellent odours, now yeeldeth in his baſe eſtate a noyſome and ſtinking ſmell. He that as yeſterday did eate the choiſeſt meates, and dranke the moſt delicate drinkes; is here become himſelfe to be the meat of wretched and loth ſome Wormes. O mortall men, let none put confidence in the delights of this life; Take example of him that lyeth here buried: who hauing poſſeſſed them, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue how little while they continued. There
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:181:47"/>is no confidence to bee placed in any but in God and in things eternall: Let theſe terrene tranſitorie worldly things bee forgotten for his loue and reuerence. Let vs follow good and holy workes which endure for euer, that with them through his Grace and Mercie, we may obtayne that eternall Life which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth for euer, and euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div n="3" type="epitaph">
                           <head>The third <hi>Epitaph.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>HEere lieth buried the terrour and feare of the Moores, Chriſtians, and Gentiles, that ploughed vp the Sea, and made the Land euen and playne. He that ſubdued the Nations of the World. The example and patterne of benigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and mercie; and the right Rule of executing Iuſtice ſeuerely, for the chaſtiſement of thoſe which do not liue vertuouſly: as the Souereigne God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth. Here resteth that liberall hand, that was neuer ſhut or cloſed to any that ſought reliefe thereof. The Protector of the poore<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Father of the Orphans; the refuge of the Widowes; the Zeale of Chastitie; The Mirrour of Honeſtie and Shamefaſtneſſe accompanied with Modeſtie; The Patterne of Princes, the Modell of Gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:181:47"/>the Picture of p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ritie and cleanneſſe; the. Type of Nobilitie; the preſeruer of truth in his Tongue; the Baniſher of Lyes; the true Louer of Learning; he that hath leſt a liuing fame of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for the future ages; and a worthy example of ſuch laſting memory as Time cannot conſume: which hath conſumed the great deeds and exployts of Kings, Princes and Emperors, burying their memory in Obliuion. O yee Mortall Men, let vs pray to our Souereigne God, that he vouchſafe to prosper and augment his memory for example of the Kings to come: that by imitation of him they may gouerne their Common-weales in Peace; dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting vs alſo to his holy Seruice; and filling vs with his Grace. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div n="4" type="epitaph">
                           <head>The fourth <hi>Epitaph.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>EVen as Gold is refined and purified in the Cruſible placed on the fire, which diſcouereth the finenes thereof among the flames: So a ſinfull man who preſerueth his patience in the perſecution of this life, doth purifie and perfect himſelfe thereby.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>A man ought to conſider that hee was borne to
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:181:48"/>ſuffer and her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                                    <desc>••</desc>
                                 </gap>ay, comfort himſelfe in this that all the trauailes of this life, ſhall haue an and with him at his death: and that only the good and holy works; are they which remayne for euer being accepted and regarded of our Souereigne God.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>O man conſider that hee created thee for his ſeruice: and that thou vngratefully haſt departed from him; without recompence of amends.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Behold how luke warme thy loue is towards him: and that of thy Creatour towards thee is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and true: hauing giuen thee thy being and accompliſhment for his Mercie.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Conſider with how high a price he hough: thee; and gaue thee meanes to ſaue thy ſelfe by vſing well thy libertie and freedome: as he hath commanded thee.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>And therefore doe I admoniſh thee that thou loſe not the much for the little; the certaine for the vncertaine: for if ſo thou doe, thou wilt find thy ſelfe deceiued.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Conſider how Miſerie and Pouertie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth not in the wanting of Parents, or Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, or of temporall goods: but in want of the fauour of God and of his Benediction.</p>
                           <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                              <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb facs="tcp:181:48"/>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
